Guide to the Larry Rubin Papers, 1961-2010 RL.11179
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Larry Rubin papers
1961-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rubin, Larry, 1942-
RL.11179
29 items
1 Linear Feet
Audio and video of meetings and activities of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee in Georgia recorded by Larry Rubin in the early 1960s; audio letters from Larry Rubin to his parents from Georgia in the early 1960s; Rubin's radio program, "Revolution in Georgia," created at Antioch College in the early 1960s; two video documentaries of the movement in Georgia featuring Rubin; two programs commemorating SNCC, dating from 2003 and 2010; papers relating to the arrest of Rubin and other SNCC/COFO members in Mississippi in 1964 for hauling books to Freedom Schools.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Biographical Note
Larry Rubin is a journalist, advocate, organizer, and public relations specialist working in the labor movement. Rubin worked in Georgia and Mississippi with the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee from 1961 to 1965, registering voters, taking depositions from those who were denied their right to vote, and organizing and participating in sit-ins and boycotts, as well as supporting unionization efforts. In 1963-1964 he worked on the Mississippi Summer Project. As a student at Antioch College, Rubin shared his experiences in the Civil Rights Movement in the Deep South via a radio show employing the recordings in this collection, which he had made in Georgia and Mississippi of SNCC meetings and other events.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Original audiovisual materials require production of listening or viewing copies prior to use. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Larry Rubin Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2016 and 2018.
Collection Overview
The collection contains six audio reels, with CD user copies, for Larry Rubin's Antioch College radio program, "Revolution in Georgia"; 18 audiocassette tapes containing recordings Rubin made in Georgia in the early 1960s (originally recorded on audio reels), of SNCC meetings and audio letters home; and three VHS videocassettes, including transferred 8mm film Rubin shot in Albany, Georgia in 1962-1963. Also includes papers that document SNCC involvement in 1964 in Mississippi and commemorative SNCC and COFO programs in the 2000s.
Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); Civil rights movements -- Georgia; Civil rights movements -- Southern States -- History -- 20th century; Albany (Ga.); Oxford (Miss.); Holly Springs (Miss.); Rubin, Larry, 1942-
- Audiovisual materials, 1961-2000; 29 items
  - Audio recordings, 1961-1988
    - Rubin family audio correspondence - Letters to and from Larry Rubin and parents, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0001)
    - "Revolution in Georgia" radio show hosted by Larry Rubin, part 1, tape 1, 1962 (Box 1, Audio-reel RL11179-RR-0001)
    - "Revolution in Georgia" radio show hosted by Larry Rubin Radio Show, part 1, tape 2, 1962 (Box 1, Audio-reel RL11179-RR-0002)
    - "Revolution in Georgia" radio show hosted by Larry Rubin, part 2, 1962 (Box 1, Audio-reel RL11179-RR-0003)
    - "Revolution in Georgia" radio show, #2, original 1/4-inch open reel audio tape, 1962 (Box 1, Audio-reel RL11179-RR-0004)
    - "Revolution in Georgia" radio show hosted by Larry Rubin, part 3, 1962 (Box 1, Audio-reel RL11179-RR-0005)
    - "Revolution in Georgia" radio show hosted by Larry Rubin, part 4, 1962 (Box 1, Audio-reel RL11179-RR-0006)
    - "Revolution in Georgia" radio show hosted by Larry Rubin, parts 1 and 2, 1962 (Box 1, Audio-cd RL11179-CD-0001)
    - "Revolution in Georgia" radio show hosted by Larry Rubin, parts 3 and 4, 1962 (Box 1, Audio-cd RL11179-CD-0002)
    - Lee County, Georgia mass meeting - includes speech by Rev. Johnson, 1962 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0007)
    - Antioch College Committee on Racial Equality (ACRE) race relations meeting, Willett Hall, Summer 1963, 1963 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0011)
    - Sumter County, GA mass meeting, 3/7/1962 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0004)
    - Terrell County, GA mass meeting, 10/21/1962 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0008)
    - Terrell County, GA (Sasser) mass meetings, speakers include Rev. CB King and Samuel Wells, 11/28/1962 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0003)
    - Terrell County, GA meeting, speakers include Mr. Trim Porter, 12/18/1962 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0002)
    - Affidavits of local people in Albany, GA describing their attempts to vote, 12/21/1962 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0009)
    - Terrell County, GA (Sasser) mass meeting, 1/29/1963 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0005)
    - WYSO (Antioch College Public Radio) radio news programs covering local protests in Xenia, OH, 9/7/1963 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0014)
    - Affidavits from women of Barry Farms Public Housing, Washington, DC re: cohabitation with men, WYSO (Antioch College Public Radio) news report on desegregation in Yellow Springs, OH, 9/16/1963 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0012)
    - Rubin family correspondence - letter from Larry Rubin to parents, 1962-07-16, 1962-11-21 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0013)
    - Rubin family correspondence - Larry Rubin to parents, 1962-12 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0015)
    - WYSO (Antioch College Public Radio) radio news programs covering memorial march for victims of Birmingham church bombing and hearings in Xenia, OH for local protests, 1963-09-22, 1963-09-24 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0018)
    - Rough cuts from "Revelution in Georgia" radio show hosted by Larry Rubin; Correspondence to Bob Ayres in Monroe, NC, January 24-25, 1964; Mass meeting recording in Monroe, NC, 1964-01-24, 1964-01-25 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0006)
    - Leet County, GA mass meetings excerpts, 1960s (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0016)
    - Freedom Singers performance at Anticoh College and "Revolution in Georgia" radio show hosted by Larry Rubin, 1960s (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0010)
    - Interview with Virginia Durr (Birmingham, AL activist) by Larry Rubin, 1/15/1988 (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL11179-CS-0017)
  - Video recordings, 1962-2000
    - Scenes from Albany, GA movement, includes activist meetings and protests downtown, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Video-cassette RL11179-VHS-0003)
    - Set on Freedom, 7/3/1994 (Box 1, Video-cassette RL11179-VHS-0001)
    - James Forman presents High Tide of Black Resistance, 2000 (Box 1, Video-cassette RL11179-VHS-0002)
- Papers
  Scope and Contents
  The Papers series contains reports, letters, and clippings relating to Rubin's arrest, along with other SNCC/COFO organizers in Mississippi in 1964. They were attempting to haul books to Freedom Schools; their subsequent arrest is referred to here as the "Book Bust." The papers also include two programs commemorating SNCC and COFO in 2003 and 2010.
  - Affidavit and search warrant for printed materials advocating the overthrow of the government of the state of Mississippi, 1964 May 6 (Box 3)
  - Council of Federated Organizations report of arrests in Holly Springs and Oxford and Larry Rubin's report, 1964 May and undated (Box 3)
    Photocopies of COFO report. Re: Larry Rubin's field report, it's almost identical to COFO report. Rubin discarded the original and re-typed the report as part of larger project for Antioch College.
  - Coverage of Eastland's speech, 1964 July 22 (Box 3)
  - Eastland's speech, 1964 July 22 (Box 3)
    Photocopy of the Congressional Record
  - Jackson Daily News on Book Bust, 1964 May 8 (Box 3)
  - John Papworth report, 1964 May-June (Box 3)
  - Letter to Attorney Bill Kuntsler regarding Eastland, 1964 July 29 (Box 3)
  - Oxford Eagle and South Report clippings about the Book Bust, 1964 May-July (Oversize-folder 1)
  - State Sovereignty Commission report of book bust, 1964 June 1 (Box 3)
  - Program for the COFO SNCC Civil Rights Celebration in Holly Springs, Mississippi at Rust College, September 18 to 21, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Program for the SNCC 50th Anniversary in Raleigh, North Carolina at Shaw University, April 15-18, 2010 (Box 3)